apple's wwdc or the worldwide developers
conference just finished and two huge
things happened first apple gave
developers one more reason why they
shouldn't make ios applications and
second apple is finally launching a
full-scale attack on passwords
nicolas
let's get started when iphone and
android first came out developers had to
make apps if they wanted to access
features such as the geolocation of the
phone
cameras contact information file system
bluetooth among other things but since
then browsers have become really really
powerful and all the things that i just
mentioned before can be done directly in
the browser using only javascript so now
if we take a look at the apps that we
have installed in our phone we might see
that apart from games a big number of
those apps don't really need to be an
app and instead they could actually be
just a website google understood this
very early on and they have been one of
the strongest supporters of pwas pwa
means progressive web application which
basically means a website that doesn't
feel like a website and it feels more
like a mobile app instead when you make
a pwa your users can install that
website on their phone install means
that they can save a shortcut to your
website in their home screen but it
won't look like a shortcut it will look
just like an app that was downloaded
from an app store when the user taps on
the icon of a saved pwa a browser window
will open but because it's a pwa the
navigation bar of the browser will be
completely hidden making it look like a
real mobile app pws are also offline
friendly we can cache some assets on the
phone meaning that if the user opens the
pwa when they are offline the app will
still open like a native app would maybe
showing some previous downloaded data or
showing something saying you are offline
the way let's say youtube does they are
also working on something called a
periodic background sync api
that will allow pws to fetch data in the
background even when the pwa is not open
but the killer feature of pwas is that
they can send push notifications to the
phone of the user like a real app would
no matter if the website is open or not
and the best of all is that because it's
just a website we don't have to go
through the review process to put our
apps on any app store i know this all
sounds too good to be true and it
actually is because there is one problem
a bitcoin pwas work amazingly well in
android phones but not so much on ios
and this makes sense apple is scared
apple is threatened by pwas
apple makes billions of dollars from the
commissions they charge to developers on
their app store they don't want websites
to be as powerful as their apps this is
why the implementation of the features
needed for pwas in ios goes a total
speed if you use ios it does not matter
if you choose to use safari or chrome or
firefox or whatever it is they might
look different but the browser engine in
ios is controlled by apple because of
this power it is still not possible to
have pwas with web push notifications on
ios they know that access to push
notifications is one of the reasons why
some companies choose to make an app
instead of making a website for years it
has been possible to make pwas with web
push notifications on android devices
but it's still not possible on ios
until now well actually no it's until
2023 but it's still good news
on the wwc apple has finally announced
that they are going to be implementing
and releasing all the features and apis
required to bring web push notifications
to the apple world it will happen first
in the desktop with safari and the
latest version of mac os which is mac os
ventura that is coming this fall and
then in 2023 web push will finally
arrive to ios and ipad os now it's just
an announcement we have to wait and see
if they actually deliver on it but it's
very good news for the web now web push
is very cool and all but the thing that
excites me the most is to see how apple
is pushing for a world without passwords
before we look into that please remember
that if you want to become a developer
and you want to do it for absolutely
free all you have to do is click the
link below there you will find free
courses on javascript python react react
native redux graphql firebase and even
go
the courses are absolutely free just
click the link below and i will see you
there it is not very often when we hear
that google apple and microsoft are all
working together on something that is
exactly what's happening right now the
tech giants are all aligned in the goal
of making passwords a thing of the past
on this wwdc apple announced the general
availability of pass kiss that is the
tech that will bring passwordless
authentication to mac ios and ipad the
reason why companies like google apple
and microsoft that are usually competing
with each other are working together in
this is because passwords absolutely
suck passwords cause all sorts of
problems and headaches for users and
developers when creating a password
people need to make them secure with
numbers uppercase and special characters
this leads to people reusing their
passwords in multiple websites because
it's hard to create a secure strong long
password for every different website
that we use which means that if one
website gets hacked and attackers gain
access to the password they can just try
the same password in many other websites
and they might take over multiple
accounts passwords are also peachable
which happens when attackers send an
email with a link to a website that
looks like a real legit website hoping
people get confused and enter their real
email and password to fix the problems
with passwords the tech industry has
come up with many different
authentication layers some websites ask
you to give them your phone number so
they can send you an sms with a
verification code which is something
that also could be hacked using
something called scene swapping
there is also a huge industry of
password managers created to store all
your passwords and generate a unique
password for every different website but
that is just centralizing all your
passwords in one place what happens if
your password provider gets hacked but
what if instead of adding all these
layers to try to make passwords strong
and verification and all those things we
can just get rid of passwords all
together fido which stands for fast
identity online is an organization that
creates standards to reduce the password
usage and those are the standards that
apple google and microsoft agreed to
implement past keys is how apple is
implementing those standards and this is
how it looks like from the point of view
of a user when going to a website and
wanting to create an account the website
will ask you if instead of using
username and password you want to use a
pass key if you do the website will show
you a qr code scanning this qr code will
create a passkey and log you in the next
time you want to log in on that website
because the passkey will be synchronized
between your phone and your computer all
you have to do is authenticate using
touch id and you can log in again as you
can see no password needed for the user
the authentication flow is super simple
all you have to do is prove that you are
the owner of your computer or your phone
using the touch id or the facial
recognition using passkeys developers
don't have to handle anything secret
from the user so if there is a leak of
data the accounts won't be compromised
pass keys are also unpieceable because
your phone will generate a unique pass
key for every different website there is
no risk of giving the wrong passkey to
the wrong website and they are also
proximity based when scanning the qr
code your phone has to be closed to the
computer that has that qr code this is
done using bluetooth which means that a
remote attack like an attacker sending
you a qr code on your email won't work
baskets can also be shared between
devices and since they are based on the
fido standard they are cross platform as
well now let's take a quick look at how
paski works behind the scenes because
it's actually super super cool when you
scan the qr code to login with passkey
what is happening is that your device is
generating a public key and a private
key this private and public key are
unique for each different website but
the private key will always stay in your
device the public key will go to the
server of the website where you are
logging in your public key isn't a
secret it can be seen by anyone and even
if they see it they still want to be
able to log into your account we can get
the public key from the private key but
we cannot do the opposite we cannot get
the private key from the public key
the private key never goes to the server
it stays in your device when you want to
sign in using pass keys the server will
send you a challenge created with your
public key the only thing that can solve
this challenge is the private key the
one in your device the solution is sent
back to the server not the private key
to understand this in an easier way
imagine that the private key is a key
and the public key is a lock when we
want to log in the server gives us a
closed look with our private key we're
going to open that lock and we're going
to give that open lock to the server
this shows to the server that we have
access to the private key but we
actually never have to give the private
key to the server just to be clear apple
did not invent this what they announced
is that they are implementing the
standard in their ecosystem passkeys are
really really good solution for
authentication here you can see how past
keys protect us against many of the
problems of using memorized passwords or
password managers on sms verification
codes i think it's pretty cool and i
cannot wait to use it to log into all my
websites and to implement it in my own
website so you can log in with it let me
know in the comments what do you think
of web push notifications finally coming
to ios are you happy is finally here did
you ever make an ios app just to have
access to notifications and what about
past keys how cool is that thank you so
much for watching stay free stay happy
stay healthy eat kimchi kamzamita
sarangayo see you on the next one bye
you